Guide to the Andover Newton Miscellaneous Personal Papers Collection
Yale University Divinity School Library
- Individuals A-L, Series I
  - Cochrane, Wilbur Willis
    - Book length typescript: "Shans of Burma and Beyond (a pre-Chinese race of China): Origin, Spread, Language, and Religion" by W.W. Cochrane, No date (Box 32, Folder 7)
    - Book length typescript: "The Story of the Shans: An Amiable and Interesting Family of Indo-China Including Relation of Buddhism to Christianity" by W.W. Cochrane, No date (Box 32, Folder 8)
    - Book length typescript: "Introductory Sketch of the History of the Shans in Upper Burma and Western Yunnan" by W. W. Cochrane, No date (Box 32, Folder 9)
    - Typescript paper: "The Sutta Nirbanna", No date (Box 32, Folder 10)
    - Typescript paper: "A Cluster of Shan Customs", No date (Box 32, Folder 11)
    - Typescript paper: "The Thais of Yunnan", No date (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - Typescript paper: "The Lay of the Land", No date (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous typescript writings, including regarding Shan folklore, No date (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous handwritten notes and writings, No date (Box 33, Folder 4-6)
    - Miscellaneous notes and writings regarding Indochinese languages, No date (Box 33, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous historical documents including proclamation of King Theebaw (1885) and rubbings of a seal, 1884-188, no date (Box 33, Folder 8)
    - Printed articles, including "Chinese Words in the Burmese Language" by Taw Sein Ko, 1906, no date (Box 33, Folder 9)
    - Materials in Shan or Indochinese script including relating to history and folklore (Box 33, Folder 10-12)
    - Materials in Shan or Indochinese script including relating to history and folklore (Box 34, Folder 1-5)
    - Scrolls in Shan or Indochinese script (Box 63, Folder 6)
  - Dabney, Vaughan
    Dabney was born in Paduch, Kentucky in 1888. He was educated at the University of Kentucky, Bethany College and Chicago Theological Seminary. He served Congregational churches in Oakland, CA (1914-1916), Durham, NH (1916-1920) and Dorchester, MA (1920-1931) before becoming Bartlet Professor of Sacred Rhetoric, President of the Andover Faculty, and Dean of Andover Newton Theological School. Following his retirement from Andover Newton in 1954 he served as interim pastor at area churches, on various boards, and as a guest lecturer and preacher. He died in 1973.
    - Documents related to tenure as pastor of First Christian Church in Oakland, CA, 1916 (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - Documents related to tenure as pastor of Congregational Church in Durham, NH, 1916-1920 (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - Documents related to tenure as pastor of Second Church of Dorchester, MA, 1920-1931 (Box 35, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence with Andover Theological Seminary and Andover Newton Theological School Board of Trustees, 1931-1954 (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - Memorabilia related to Andover Newton, 1947-1969 (Box 35, Folder 5)
    - Appointment book, 1941 (Box 35, Folder 6)
    - Genealogical book about Dabney family of Virginia, 1888 (Box 35, Folder 7)
    - Photographs, including portraits of Dabney and with wife; 1954 class photo for Andover Newton Theological School, 1939, 1954, no date (Box 35, Folder 8)
    - Photographs and documents removed from scrapbook (Box 35, Folder 9)
    - Articles about Dabney; program from memorial service, 1932-1973 (Box 35, Folder 10)
  - Davis, Jacob
    Jacob Davis was born in Dighton, MA, August 16, 1812. After his conversion as a young man he felt called to ministry and began a course of study by himself, while continuing work at his trade of masonry and building construction. Some sources indicate that he studied at Andover Theological Seminary ca.1838; however, there is no record of his emollment in school records. He was licensed to preach by North Baptist Church, Dorchester, MA. For several years he served as a pulpit supply in area churches and continued working in his trade. He was ordained as pastor of the Baptist church in North Marshfield, MA, in 1863. He had succeeding pastorates in Florida, MA, 1870-1878, and Rowe, MA, 1878-1889. Upon his retirement he returned to Marshfield, where he died October 22,1903.
    - Diaries, 1868-1886 (Box 36, Folder 1-8)
    - Correspondence, including to sister, from son George Davis, from J.P. Blanchard (for full listing of letters see original finding aid at repository), 1844-1901, no date (Box 36, Folder 9)
    - Undated sermons arranged by text (for full listing of texts, see original finding aid at repository), No date (Box 36, Folder 10-11)
    - Dated sermons (for full listing of texts and titles, see original finding aid in repository), 1860-1861 (Box 36, Folder 12-13)
    - Dated sermons, 1862-1893 (Box 37, Folder 1-5)
    - Addresses, including "Immortality Revealed", "The Gospel and its Foes", 1878-1893, no date (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Unpublished manuscripts, including "The Atonement in its Relation to Man", "Encouragement for the Sorrowful", No date (Box 37, Folder 7)
    - Scientific notes, primarily related to astronomy, 1838-1868 (Box 37, Folder 8)
    - Meteorological records for Rowe, Franklin County, MA, 1880-1882 (Box 37, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 37, Folder 10-11)
  - Denison, Frederic
    Denison was born in Mt. Vernon, NY on September 28, 1819. He graduated from Brown University in 1847 and was ordained as a Baptist minister. He served Baptist churches in Westerly, RI (1847-1854, 1866-1871), Norwich, CT (1854-1859), Central Falls, RI (1860-1861), and New Haven, CT (1872). Denison was a chaplain and Assistant Allotment Commissioner in the U.S. military service from 1861 to 1864. Following his ministerial work, Denison was an author until his death in Providence, RI in 1901.
    - Scrapbook containing programs and bulletins, including many commencement programs from New England colleges and universities from the early 19th century (Box 74, Folder 1)
    - Scrapbook containing primarily newspaper clippings, mostly about Rhode Island history; also many poems and articles published by Denison, 1886-1891 (Box 74, Folder 2)
    - Scrapbook containing primarily newspaper clippings, mostly about Rhode Island history; also many poems and articles published by Denison, 1891-1898 (Box 75, Folder 1)
    - Additional programs and flyers relating to Brown University and Pembroke Hall, including commencement programs, Class Day exercises, plays, concerts, 1868-1909 (Box 75, Folder 2-4)
    - Manuscript and typescript poems by Denison (Box 76, Folder 1-2)
    - Sermons and essays (Box 76, Folder 3)
    - Autobiographical and biographical writings (Box 76, Folder 4)
  - Dodge, William Bradford
    Dodge was born on September 27, 1783 in Rowley, Essex, MA. He taught school in Salem, MA and served as chaplain of the Salem Almshouse. An ardent abolitionist, Dodge used his home as a stop in the Underground Railroad. In 1834 he gave up his position at the North School in Salem to run the newly formed "colored school." By 1842 William gave up teaching to concentrate fully on the anti-slavery movement. He moved to Illinois in 1844 and served a Congregational church there. He died in 1869.
    - Correspondence: four letters from Dodge to his grandson Henry Leavitt Dodge, written from Millburn, IL, 1856, 1863, 1864, no date (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - Sermons: seven manuscript sermons arranged chronologically, 1830, 1833, 1849, 1857, no date (Box 38, Folder 2)
    - Addresses: "The Doom of Slavery; a lecture on the certainty of the ultimate success of the Abolition cause" (1840); Anti-slavery address over which an article detailing slavery laws is pasted (no date), 1840, no date (Box 38, Folder 3)
    - Bound volume: "A Memorandum of Texts discoursed from at the Salem Alms House" Volume covers January 1, 1834 to December 30, 1855 and includes death statistics from May 5, 1827 to January 1, 1834., 1827-1855 (Box 38, Folder 4)
    - One manuscript sheet containing genealogical information about Thomas Leavitt (1763-179?) (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - Donovan, Winfred
    Donovan was born January 24, 1869 in Belchertown, MA. He graduated from Colby College (1892)and Newton Theological Institution (1898), and studied at the University of Berlin, 1913-1914. He taught Old Testament at Newton Theological Institution from 1915 to 1942 and served as Secretary of the Faculty at Andover Newton.
    - Notes and minutes from Andover Newton faculty meetings and retreats, 1934-1942 (Box 39, Folder 1-4)
    - Correspondence relating to duties as Secretary of Faculty, including some addresses to President E. C. Herrick, 1938-1942 (Box 39, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous documents relating to Andover Newton curriculum, students, thesis topics, etc., 1934-1942 (Box 39, Folder 6)
    - Notes and outlines related to teaching of Old Testament (Box 39, Folder 7)
  - Dunbar, Robert Wayland
    Dunbar graduated from Andover Theological Seminary in 1898. He served Congregational churches in North Chelmsford, MA (1899-1904), Haverhill, MA (1904-1909), Millbury, MA (1909-1918), Greenville and Mason, NH (1918-1923). He died in Greenville in 1923.
    - Documents related to Dunbar's ministerial service, 1897-1918 (Box 40, Folder 1-2)
    - Statements of why he entered the ministry, No date (Box 40, Folder 3)
    - Pastoral journal containing list of sermons preached, marriages performed, church members, etc., 1898-1919 (Box 40, Folder 3)
    - Typescript talks and papers presented, including on Athanasius, Hildebrand, Savonarola, and "What Should the Christian Citizen do for the Immigrant?", 1904-1907, no date (Box 40, Folder 4-5)
    - Documents related to Second Congregational Church, Millbury, MA and West Congregational Church, Haverhill, MA, 1882-1908 (Box 40, Folder 6)
  - Dyer, Vernelle Wallace
    Dyer was born in 1894 in Saugus, MA. He graduated from Colby College in 1915 and from Newton Theological Institution in 1919. He was ordained December 14, 1917, by Oakland Baptist Church in Waterville, ME. Dyer served for 20 years as a missionary in Burma under sponsorship of the American Baptist Foreign Mission Society, 1919-1939. While in Burma he was pastor of Immanuel Baptist Church in Rangoon, 1919-1925, and was a founder and leader of Burma College Gospel Teams, 1923-1939. In 1927 he also co-founded Northern Baptist Seminary in Burma. Dyer's pastoral service in the United States was at the following Baptist churches: Roger Williams Baptist Church, Providence, RI, 1940-1943; Clarksburg, WV, 1946- 1947; Bar Harbor, ME, 1949-1956, and Belfast, ME, 1956-1962. He also served as a U.S. Army Chaplain, 1942-1946. In retirement Dyer lived in Milbridge, ME, until his death in October 1974.
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift of Stephen Fisher, 1993.
    - Correspondence, primarily to Dyer, including from colleagues in Burma. For full list of correspondents see original finding aid available at repository, 1932-1936 (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - Sermons and addresses, including "Christ of the Burma Road" and "Burma Students Gospel Teams", 1932-1933, no date (Box 41, Folder 2)
    - Photographs of family and friends in the U.S. and in Asia (Box 41, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous collected material (Box 41, Folder 4)
  - Eaton, William Harrison
    Eaton was born February 22, 1841 in Hopkinton, NH. He graduated from Colby College and was ordained as a Baptist minister, serving churches in Goffstown, NH, Amesbury, MA, and Westfield, MA. From 1888 he was Secretary of the Massachusetts Baptist Missionary Society and Convention. He died in Medford, MA in 1908.
    - Correspondence and documents related to Eaton family genealogy and Eaton Family Association, 1882, 1887-1908, no date (Box 42, Folder 1-5)
    - Letters of reference for persons making application for pastorates under Massachusetts Baptist Convention, arranged alphabetically: A-M / Lists of names in first folder, 1888-1908 (Box 42, Folder 6-15)
    - Letters of reference for persons making application for pastorates under Massachusetts Baptist Convention, arranged alphabetically: N-Z (Box 43, Folder 1-6)
  - Edwards, Jonathan, Jr.
    Edwards, the son of Jonathan Edwards (1703-1758), was born on May 26, 1745 in Northampton, Massachusetts. He graduated from Princeton University in 1765 and studied theology with Joseph Bellamy in Bethlehem, Connecticut during 1765-1766, becoming licensed to preach in 1766. From 1767 to 1769 he was a tutor at Princeton University. He was minister of the White Haven Church in New Haven, Connecticut from 1769 to 1795 and in Colebrook, Connecticut from 1796 to 1799. Edwards was President of Union College from 1799 until his death on August 1, 1801.
    - Correspondence, including letter to Timothy Dwight, 1773-1782 (Box 168, Folder 1)
    - Sermons, 1769-1801, no date (Box 168, Folder 2-15)
      For a full listing of scriptural texts and dates of the sermons, see Box 168, Folder 2.
    - Order of Commencement, Union College, 1801 May 6 (Box 168, Folder 16)
  - Emmons, Nathanael
    Emmons was born in Connecticut on April 20, 1749. He graduated from Yale College in 1767 and studied theology with various Connecticut ministers from 1767 to 1769. He was a preacher at various locations from 1769 to 1773 and then served as minister of the Congregational Church in Franklin, MA from 1773 to 1827. He died on September 23, 1840 in Franklin, MA.
    - Two manuscript sermons, on texts Matthew 8:20 (1795) and Psalm 37:4 (1809), 1795, 1809 (Box 63, Folder 5)
  - Evans, Daniel
    Evans was born August 22, 1866 in South Wales. He attended Bowdoin College and graduated from Bangor Theological Seminary in 1889. He was ordained in 1891 and served churches in East Weymouth, MA (1891-1899) and Cambridge, MA (1899-1908). In 1908 he was appointed Abbot Professor of Christian Theology at Andover Thelogical Seminary.
    - Undated sermons (Box 45, Folder 1)
    - Dated sermons, 1899-1910 (Box 45, Folder 2-16)
      A list of scriptural texts and titles of the sermons is in the first folder.
    - Dated sermons, 1911-1927 (Box 46, Folder 1-13)
    - Undated chapel talks (Box 46, Folder 14)
    - Dated chapel talks, 1908-1940 (Box 46, Folder 15-19)
    - Addresses and articles, 1903-1932 (Box 47, Folder 1-18)
      Titles include: "The Working Man and the Church", "The New Social Consciousness", "Darwin and Lincoln", "How Can New Life and Power be put into the New England Unitarian Churches?", "The Censorship of Books"
    - Bound lecture notes (2 volumes): "Lectures on the Philosophy of Religion and Philosophical Papers"; "Lectures on Christian Ethics" (Box 48)
  - Fackre, Gabriel
    Fackre was born in 1926 in Jersey City, NJ. He attended Bucknell University and received his B.D. and Ph.D. from the University of Chicago. Fackre was Professor of Theology and Culture at Lancaster Theological Seminary from 1961 to 1970. He was Samuel Abbot Professor of Christian Theology at Andover Newton Theological School from 1971 to 1996. Fackre was a prominent theologian and active in social justice and ecumenical activities. He died in Oregon City, OR on January 31, 2018.
    This collection primarily documents Fackre's correspondence and activities as a faculty member at Andover Newton Theological School. It does not include scholarly writings or notes.
    - Correspondence and memos related to Fackre's duties as faculty member at Andover Newton Theological School, 1971-1984 (Box 84, Folder 1-10)
    - Correspondence and memos related to Fackre's duties as faculty member, and as faculty emeritus, at Andover Newton Theological School, 1985-2008 (Box 85, Folder 1-11)
    - Correspondence with pastors and church leaders: A - P (Box 86, Folder 1-15)
    - Correspondence with pastors and church leaders: R - Z (Box 87, Folder 1-8)
    - Correspondence with laity (Box 87, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence with parishioners (Box 87, Folder 10-11)
    - Correspondence with students (Box 87, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence related to "Theological Tabletalk" (Box 88, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence with Andover Newton faculty secretary, Kay Coughlin (Box 88, Folder 1)
    - Office files: Laity Project, 1976-1991 (Box 88, Folder 3-8)
    - Office files: Miscellaneous (Box 88, Folder 9-14)
    - Typescript essay regarding Andover Newton in the 1980s (Box 88, Folder 15)
    - Syllabi (Box 88, Folder 16)
    - Obituary and photo of Fackre (Box 88, Folder 17)
  - Fisher, Abial
    Fisher was born June 19, 1787 in Putney, VT. He graduated from the University of Vermont in 1811 and studied theology with Nathaniel Kendrick in Middlebury, VT 1811-1815. He was ordained in Brandon, VT in 1815 and served Baptist churches in Bellingham, MA (1816-1827), West Boylston, MA (1828-1831), Sturbridge, MA (1832), Webster, MA (1833-1834), Pawtuxet, RI (1835-1836), Swansea, MA (1837-1845), and Sutton, MA (1855-1857). He died in 1862
    - Numbered sermons, #11-27, 1813, no date (Box 49, Folder 1-6)
      Titles include:"The scriptures a revelation from God", "The trinity and unity of the Godhead", "On the nature of divine providence as it respects angels and men"
    - Unnumbered sermons, arranged by text (Box 49, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous documents, including "Articles of faith and practice", "Swansea Baptist Church subscription for foreign missions", letter from [S. Hall] to Fisher, from North Swansea, 1846, 1855, no date (Box 49, Folder 8)
  - Fiske, Daniel Taggert
    Fiske was born in Shelburne, MA on March 29, 1819. He graduated from Amherst College in 1842 and received a certificate from Andover Theological Seminary in 1846. He was ordained as a Congregational minister on August 18, 1847 and served the Belleville Congregational Church in Newburyport, MA from 1847 to 1887. He was a lecturer on Systematic Theology at Andover Theological Seminary 1881-1882. He died in Newburyport on January 15, 1903.
    - Unnumbered sermons (Box 50, Folder 1)
      A full listing of texts and titles of all sermons in the collection is available in this folder.
    - Numbered sermons, #2-317 (some numbers missing) (Box 50, Folder 2-34)
    - Numbered sermons, #321-523 (some numbers missing) (Box 51, Folder 1-19)
    - Numbered sermons, #970-992 (some numbers missing) (Box 52, Folder 1-4)
    - Addresses, lectures, essays, including: "Scottish songs and songwriters", "Aesthetic culture", "An address for Christmas", 1832, 1841, 1886, no date (Box 52, Folder 5-6)
    - Miscellaneous documents including 3 fragments and copy of essay by William Silsbee, 1831, no date (Box 52, Folder 7)
    - Papers related to the trials of Andover professors on charges of heresy, including Prof. Egbert C. Smyth and Prof. W. H. Ryder, "received from the library of the late Daniel T. Fiske, 1906" (Box 53)
      Includes proceedings from court trials of Andover professors accused of heresy, a paper prepared by Daniel T. Fiske "to be used before the Visitors of Andover Seminary in case Prof. Smyth was retired on the old charges" (1892), pamphlets, including: "The Creed of Andover Theological Seminary by Rev. D. T. Fiske" (2 editions), "The Associate Creed of Andover Theological Seminary by Edwards A. Park", "Report of the Committee on Litigation, made to the Trustees of Phillips Academy"
  - Gilkey, James Gordon
    Gilkey was born September 28, 1889 in Watertown MA. He graduated from Harvard College (1912) and Union Theological Seminary in New York. Following a time as chaplain and teacher at Amherst College, he served the South Congregational Church in Springfield, MA from 1917 to 1954. He died in July 1964 in Weekapaug, RI.
    - Sermons, 1929-1944 (Box 54, Folder 1-13)
    - Sermons, 1944-1953 (Box 55, Folder 1-6)
    - Essays: "Toward a Fourth Major Form of Christianity" and "Liberal Protestantism - Its Positive Religious Teachings" (printed for private distribution), 1962, 1963 (Box 55, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous lectures and articles, 1941, 1942, no date (Box 55, Folder 8)
    - Lectures on Biblical literature, 1923-1924, no date (Box 56, Folder 1-4)
    - Lectures to Parents, 1933-1936 (Box 56, Folder 5)
    - Classes for Church Young People, 1935-1938 (Box 56, Folder 6)
    - Lectures at Springfield College (Box 56, Folder 7-8)
    - Lectures in Hartford and Northfield, 1946-1949 (Box 56, Folder 9)
    - Bible Courses, 1950-1952 (Box 56, Folder 10)
  - Gulliver, John Putnam
    Gulliver was born May 12, 1819 in Boston, MA. He graduated from Yale College in 1840 and did theological studies at Yale during 1843-1844. He received a certificate from Andover Theological Seminary in 1845 and a Resident licentiate in 1846. He was ordained as a Congregational minister on October 1, 1846 and served the Broadway Congregational Church, Norwich, CT (1845-1865), the New England Congregational Church, Chicago (1865-1868) and First Presbyterian Church, Binghamton, NY (1872-1878). From 1868 to 1872 he was President of Knox College in Galesburg, IL. He was Stone Professor of the Relations of Christianity and Science at Andover Theological Seminary from 1878 to 1894. He died in Andover, MA January 25, 1894.
    - Lectures: undated fragments (Box 57, Folder 1-4)
    - Single lectures, including "Lecture on the Theories of Moral Obligation" and "The relations of Zoology to Biblical interpretation" (Box 57, Folder 5-6)
    - Course lectures and syllabi, Andover Theological Seminary: Junior Year, including "The scientific application of the cognitive process to Theology" and "Syllabus of Div. G--the application of the scientific process already ascribed to Theology", 1884-1886, no date (Box 57, Folder 7-14)
    - Course lectures and syllabi, ATS: Middle Year, including "Science in Theology", No date (Box 57, Folder 15-35)
    - Course lectures and syllabi, ATS: Middle Year, including "Science in Theology", "Cognition and Agnosticism", 1881-1891 (Box 58, Folder 1-19)
    - Course lectures and syllabi, ATS: Senior Year, including "Course in Biology", "Course in Evolution", 1880, no date (Box 58, Folder 20-29)
    - Course lectures and syllabi, ATS: Senior Year, including "Lectures on Evolution", "Theology and Cosmology", 1881-1888 (Box 59, Folder 1-28)
    - Course lectures and syllabi, ATS: Senior Year, including "Theology among the Sciences", 1889-1890 (Box 60, Folder 1-9)
    - Course lectures and syllabi, ATS: Fourth Year, including "Theological Methodology", 1881-1883, no date (Box 60, Folder 10-24)
    - Addresses, including on evolution, on "the changes in New England Calvinism since the introduction of modern science and philosophy", No date (Box 60, Folder 25-27)
    - Addresses, including "The theistic argument as affected by recent Philosophy and Science", 1880. no date (Box 61, Folder 1-5)
    - Unpublished manuscripts: three articles on Darwin's theory of evolution, No date (Box 61, Folder 6)
    - Published manuscript: "Have Modern Philosophical or Scientific Investigations Modified or Set Aside any Doctrine of Evangelical Christianity as held by Edwards and the Calvinists of New England in his Day? (published in The Golden Rule ), circa 1881-1882 (Box 61, Folder 7-8)
    - Published manuscript: "A Symposium on Evolution. Is the Darwinian Theory of Evolution Reconcilable with the Bible? If So, with What Limitations. (published in the Homiletic Monthly 8 /July, 1884: 591-597.) (Box 61, Folder 9-11)
    - Questions for examination and review, No date (Box 61, Folder 12)
  - Hall, Robert Beals
    Hall was born December 30, 1845 in Ashfield, MA. He graduated from Williams College in 1870 and from Union Theological Seminary in 1873. He received a licenciate from Andover Theological Seminary in 1873. He served churches in Wolfeboro, NH (1873-1875)and Cambridgeport, MA (1875-1876) before his death on November 2, 1876.
    - Numbered sermons: #1-96, circa 1873-1876 (Box 69, Folder 1-17)
    - Sermon fragments, unnumbered writings (Box 69, Folder 18)
    - Untitled essay, 1868 (Box 69, Folder 19)